# Jaime Cisternas Riquelme Informatic Engineer

jcr\_mw@yahoo.com (801) 931 0638

Portfolio: <a href="https://jecisternas.github.io">https://jecisternas.github.io</a>

Wide variety of professional experience; IT tasks, software development, web development, networking. Ability to understand and address any topic, very curious about different study areas, creative to find solutions, investigative, strong self-learning.

# **WORK EXPERIENCE**

2021 Present – <u>Warehouse Organizer</u>. Renewal by Andersen Salt Lake City <u>www.renewalbyandersen.com</u>.

• Improved the management of the warehouse inventory. The company didn't have any system to manage the inventory. So, I Developed and implemented a new system. It vastly improved the scheduling process making it easier, faster, and more accurate, and let handle the information when the number of jobs scheduled increased. The system is based on Microsoft Excel worksheets and VBA Language.

# 2020 -2021 - Management of Retirement Funds Advisory.

• I taught many Chilean people in Chile and in U.S how to access the system, how to manage the account to increase their funds, and how to withdraw money according to the last legislation.

# 2012 - 2019. - Freelance Web Development.

- Improving my career continuously. Added knowledge about web development like HTML, CSS, JavaScript.
- Developed websites to show information about activities for different organizations and independent people. Ex: Camport <u>www.camport.cl</u>, DSIC. <u>www.dsic.pucv.cl</u>, Institute of Art <u>www.arte.ucv.cl</u>, Ximena Cuadra Art <u>www.ximenacuadra.cl</u>.

2005 -2019. – <u>Newspaper Distributor</u>. Media One / Wasatch Newspaper Distributor.

- In charge of newspaper distribution.
- Carrier's supplies provider.

2005 -2005. – Migrated to United States of America.

 Retained relationship with some customers in Chile doing software maintenance.

# 2000 -2005. - Freelance Software Development.

- Developed Applications for handheld Symbols, Palm PDA, and Pocket PC.
- "Mobile Wallet": Achieved 100% of success avoiding overdraft on bank account with this mobile application. It was run as personal and small businesses.
- "Inventory Count", used by large warehouses to make the inventory like Mattel Chile.
- Ernst & Young S.A used it on "Jumbo Supermarket" www.jumbo.cl, and Easy Home Store www.easy.cl.
- Improvements processes, saving time, money, reducing efforts, increasing accuracy, and getting better results for Turbus Chile Ltda. <a href="www.turbus.cl">www.turbus.cl</a>, Chilepost S.A. <a href="www.chilepost.cl">www.chilepost.cl</a>, Whirlpool Chile Ltda. <a href="www.whirlpool.cl">www.whirlpool.cl</a>, DIN S.A. <a href="www.din.cl">www.din.cl</a>, HTS Santiago Chile <a href="www.hts.cl">www.fruitonline.com</a>, and other..
- Minimarket Store Owner.

1990 -1999. - Systems and Communication Department Manager. - LDS Church Office, Santiago, Chile.

- In Charge of purchases, computers inventory, backup, documentation, and extract information about Church Membership from the Oracle database.
- Covered a range of different tasks like management, IT, software development, training, networking, hardware maintenance, etc. Assisted more than one hundred users on hardware and application use.
- The most important achievement was the installation of the Local Area Network. With little knowledge at the beginning and after self-learning we installed network cards, hubs, switches, router, PC's setup, etc.

1989 -1990 - Project Manager

EuroAmerica S.A. (Insurance Company). Santiago, Chile. www.euroamerica.cl

- Lead project to migrate systems programmed in COBOL and RPG from mainframe IBM S/36 to IBM AS/400.
- Programmed and implemented new procedures in COBOL and RPG.

1988 -1989 - <u>Project Manager, Analyst, Programmer</u> S.T.Computacion, Santiago, Chile. <u>www.st.cl</u>

- Acquired huge experience participating in the development team, analyzing, designing, programming, and documenting integrated administrative systems (Purchases, Sales, Inventory, Clients, Providers, Accounting and Payroll).
- Managed a programmer team achieving a high level of commitment and integration in the team.
- Technology used: COBOL and implemented in IBM S/36 and IBM AS/400 mainframes.
- Replaced the information system documentation with a new one making it more graphics, didactic and easier to understand by developers and users.

1986 -1988 - Project Manager, Analyst, Programmer DGTM (Navy). Valparaíso, Chile. <a href="www.directemar.cl">www.directemar.cl</a>

- Managed a programmer team, for maintenance of software to control Commercial Navy traffic, Government Accounting, and Payroll.
- Trained staff in applications running on PC's.
- Technology used: COBOL language, IBM S/36, PC's, Macintosh.

1985 -1986 - Teacher and Trainer

Technical Training Center C.E.I.M.A. (No longer active). Viña del Mar, Chile

 Taught programming languages in regular classes, and trained professionals about structured analysis, system specifications, and logical derivation equivalents files to model relational databases.

## **REFERENCES**

Guillermo Antivilo – Director of Production and Distribution Division Welfare and Reliance Department, Salt Lake City. Ryan Johns - Xactware, Lehi.

Rosalie Pederson - Chisl Inc.

### **EDUCATION**

03/1980 - 11/1984 - Informatics Engineer Federico Santa Maria University. Valparaiso, Chile, www.usm.cl.

U.S. Equivalence, **BA Computer Science**. Evaluated by Educational Credential Evaluators (ECE) in U.S., www.ece.org. Reference: C88408. http://myjcrweb.com/img/cert/ECE.jpeg.

2019 Fall Semester - Courses (On-Campus) Salt Lake Community College, Taylorsville, Utah. www.slcc.edu.

Java / HTML-CSS-JavaScript / Linux.

#### Online courses

IBM Courses, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Git, GitHub, Testing, Data Science(

https://www.youracclaim.com/users/jaimecisternas.2ac03e86/badges).

#### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

Management, Structured Analysis & System Specification. Database Modeling. Systems Development

**Programming Languages and Databases** 

COBOL, Visual Basic, Java, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, SQL, React.

#### Tools

Data Science Tools, Data Modeler, Visual Studio Code, Visual Paradigm, Adobe Illustrator, Git, GitHub. Microsoft Office, Windows and MacOS.

#### **SOFT SKILLS**

Attention to detail, Research & Analysis. Creativity to find solutions. Curiosity. Adaptability, Dedication, Confidence, Commitment and Concentration at work.

LANGUAGES. English, Spanish.